{"tossups": [{"question": "This man's namesake homestead lies in the Winooski [[weh-\"NEW\"-skee]] Valley, and this American rejected the \"crown of Massachusetts\" by Daniel Shay to assist in his revolt. The Governor of Quebec began negotiations with this man in what became the Haldimand Affair, an effort by the British to annex a fledgling republic. With Benedict Arnold and a Connecticut militia, this man forced the surrender of Fort Ticonderoga. The leader of the Green Mountain Boys was, for the point, which Vermont hero of the Revolutionary War?", "answer": "Ethan <b><u>Allen</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this event, the son of the eventual victor unsuccessfully attempted to beseige Ueda [[OO-eh-dah]] Castle. Prior to this event, Ishida Mitsunari claimed Osaka Castle and planned to force hostages to join his side. This decisive event ended the Sengoku, or \"Warring States, period in one country, which followed after the death of Toyotomi Hideyoshi. For the point, name this decisive battle often seen as the unofficial beginning of the Tokugawa shogunate.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Sekigahara</u></b> (or <b><u>Sekigahara</u></b> no Tatakai)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In the 1930s, Austrian chemist Fritz Johann Hansgirg built a plant to produce this compound in Japanese-occupied Korea. Norsk Hydro built the first commercial plant for production of this compound, and its destruction was the subject of the failed British Operation Freshman. Operation Gunnerside saw the destruction of that facility for this compound by Norwegian commandos in order to inhibit Nazi Germany's ability to develop nuclear weapons. For the point, name this compound of oxygen and two deuterium atoms, historically used as a moderator for nuclear uranium reactors.", "answer": "<b><u>Heavy Water</u></b> (or <b><u>Deuterium Oxide</u></b>; or <b><u>D2O</u></b> or <b><u>2H2O</u></b>; prompt on \"Deuterium\"; do not accept or prompt on \"water\" or \"H2O\")", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "This port was temporarily blockaded during a 1918 British operation under John Jellicoe which sank obsolete battleships in this city's harbor. William Caxton created the first English language book using the newly created printing press in this European city. The massacre of a French garrison during this Belgian city's namesake \"Matins\" [[mah-TEEN]] led to the Battle of the Golden Spurs in the Franco-Flemish war. The World War One Battle of Courtrai liberated, for the point, what North Sea port in West Flanders?", "answer": "<b><u>Bruges</u></b> (accept <b><u>Brugge</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The first major success in this campaign was the deposition of Khan Kuchum by Yermak Timofeyevich's forces. Dmitry Pavlutsky's attempt at a genocide of the Chukchi during this campaign was thwarted by an overwhelming loss near Markovo. The Ostyuks, Voguls, and Buriat were among the peoples who were colonized during this process. For the point, identify this approximately century-long process beginning in 1580 by which the vast eastern portion of present-day Russia was brought under the tsars' control.", "answer": "Russian <b><u>conquest of Siberia</u></b> (or <b><u>colonization of Siberia</u></b>; accept answers referring to <b><u>Siberia</u></b> or the <b><u>Sibir</u></b> Khanate being explored, organized, or annexed by or to Russia or Muscovy or the Russian Empire)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This dynasty declined during rebellions led by Wang Xianzhi [[SHYAN-ZHEE]] and Huang Chao. The death penalty was ended during this dynasty\u2019s golden age under Emperor Xuanzong. This dynasty ended the G\u04e7kt\u00fcrk Khaganate and encountered the Abbasids at the Talas River. Arab mercenaries were employed by this dynasty to defeat a rebellious Sogdian general, An Lushan. For the point, identify this Chinese dynasty that experienced an interregnum from the only legitimized Chinese Empress, Wu Zetian.", "answer": "<b><u>Tang</u></b> Dynasty (or <b><u>T\u00e1ng</u></b>ch\u00e1o; accept D\u00e0 <b><u>T\u00e1ng</u></b>; or Great <b><u>Tang</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "After this conflict, its namesake fled to Mount Hope where he was killed by John Alderman, a member of a group of rangers led by Benjamin Church. This conflict was initiated by the hanging of three Native Americans in one colony, and it included the lopsided victory in the Great Swamp Fight. The Treaty of Casco Bay ended, for the point, which war between indigenous people and the New England Confederation, named for a Wampanoag [[wahm-pah-NOH-ahg]] chief?", "answer": "<b><u>King Philip</u></b>'s War (or The <b><u>First Indian</u></b> War, <b><u>Metacom</u></b>'s War, <b><u>Metacomet</u></b>'s War, <b><u>Pometacomet's Rebellion</u></b>, or <b><u>Metacom's Rebellion</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Almost 7,000 people who died during this event were cremated on the <em>Altmarkt</em> square. This event was planned as an alteration of Operation Thunderclap against Berlin. Despite a U.S. Air Force report determining that strategic targets like a railway junction and poison gas plant were destroyed, this event convinced Winston Churchill to lobby against \"morale bombings.\" For the point, name this winter 1945 attack on a German city in Saxony that resulted in a devastating firestorm.", "answer": "<b><u>Bombing</u></b> of <b><u>Dresden</u></b> (accept <b><u>Dresden</u></b> firestorm; accept equivalents)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One man in this election faced accusations of wanting to form a monarchical dynasty and was called \u201cHis Rotundity\" by detractors. \"Phocion\" claimed one of the leading candidates in this election cycle was having an affair with a female slave. This election, which motivated the passage of the 12th amendment, is considered the beginning of the \"First Party System\" in the U.S. between the Federalist and Democratic-Republican parties. The first contested presidential run occurred during, for the point, which election between Thomas Jefferson and its winner, John Adams?", "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of <b><u>1796</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man's atrocities were described by George Washington Wallace with one of the first uses of the phrase, \"crimes against humanity.\" Those crimes committed by this man and the Force Publique came to light in the Casement Report. During this man\u2019s reign, he sent Henry Morton Stanley to explore Africa\u2019s present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo. Serving the longest reign of any Belgian monarch, for the point, name this second King of the Belgians and notorious personal owner of the Congo Free State.", "answer": "<b><u>Leopold II</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man unsuccessfully ran for office three times before beating Anita Bryant and Rick Stokes to become city supervisor. A speech given by this man in opposition to the Briggs Initiative was later called the \u201cHope Speech.\u201d Alongside Mayor George Moscone, this man was assassinated by Dan White, whose lawyers utilized the infamous \"Twinkie Defense\" to avoid murder charges. For the point, name this San Francisco politician who was the first openly gay elected official in the history of California.", "answer": "Harvey Bernard <b><u>Milk</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A commander in this war brought troops across the Pikysyry [[pee-KEE-see-REE]] River during a series of three victories at Ytoror\u00f3 [[ee-toh-ROH-roh]], Avay, and Lomas Valentinas that comprised the \"Deed of December.\" This was the last war in which the Duke of Caxias [[kah-SHEE-us]] commanded troops in battle. During this war's climactic Battle of Cerro Cor\u00e1, the dictator Francisco Solano L\u00f3pez was killed. Up to 90% of the losing country's male population died in this war. For the point, name this late 1860s war in which Paraguay lost to Uruguay, Argentina, and Brazil.", "answer": "War of the <b><u>Triple Alliance</u></b> (or Guerra de la <b><u>Triple Alianza</u></b> or Guerra da <b><u>Tr\u00edplice</u></b> <b><u>Alian\u00e7a</u></b>; accept <b><u>Paraguyan</u></b> War before \"Paraguay\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This woman is sometimes considered the first female ambassador in European history for representing her sister, Joanna, in a certain court. This woman authored a possibly fictive letter asking her nephew, Emperor Charles V, to protect her daughter. That girl's father was a king this woman married after the death of his elder brother, her first husband, Arthur, Prince of Wales. This woman died in Kimbolton Castle some time after her husband divorced her for her lady-in-waiting, Anne Boleyn. For the point, name this queen consort of England and first wife of King Henry VIII.", "answer": "<b><u>Catherine of Aragon</u></b> (or <b><u>Catalina de Arag\u00f3n</u></b>; prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This state's police force was known as the <em>assara-munidios</em>, or \"Enforcers,\" who not only arrested criminals but also acted as jurists. An Islamic convert from Castile named Judar Pasha razed this empire's salt mines in Taghaza [[tah-gah-ZAH]] during an invasion. This empire's Askia Dynasty fled south after a Moroccan invasion led to Askia Ishaq II's [[ee-SHAK the Second's]] deposition following the Battle of Tondibi. The Mali empire was overthrown by, for the point, what West African state governed from Gao [[GOW]]?", "answer": "<b><u>Songhai</u></b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A man with this name, likely deriving from the minor deity Pummay, built early settlements on Sardinia as described in the Nora Stone. That king with this name orchestrated the killing of his sister's husband and fellow royal Acerbas, prompting his wife Dido to flee Phoenicia to found the city of Carthage. An artist with this name prayed to Aphrodite to bring his statue of Galatea to life. A George Bernard Shaw play derives its name from, for the point, what Cypriot sculptor of Greek myth?", "answer": "<b><u>Pygmalion</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Donald Trump\u2019s envoy Richard Grenell pressured this country\u2019s LDK Party to leave its ruling coalition. A prime minister of this country named Hashim Tha\u00e7i [[THAH-chee]] worked to normalize relations with its northern neighbor in the Brussels Agreement. This country\u2019s KLA was labeled a terrorist group by Slobodan Milo\u0161evi\u0107 [[mee-LOH-seh-vich]]. This country declared its independence in 2008, largely due to its majority-Albanian population. For the point, name this partially-recognized country claimed by Serbia and governed from Pristina.", "answer": "<b><u>Kosovo</u></b> (or <b><u>Kosova</u></b>; or <b><u>Kosov\u00eb</u></b>; accept Republic of <b><u>Kosovo</u></b>; or Republika e <b><u>Kosov\u00eb</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "During an early phase of popularity for this instrument, it was used to play the <em>Valse</em> <em>Erica</em> by Rudy Wiedoeft. The lead player on <em>Somethin' Else</em> used this instrument and recorded the crossover hit \"Mercy Mercy Mercy.\" This instrument played by Cannonball Adderley was used by the composer of \"Ko-Ko\" to pioneer bebop and is the lead instrument on the \"Yardbird Suite.\" For the point, name this kind of instrument whose \"alto\" variety was played by Charlie Parker.", "answer": "<b><u>Saxophone</u></b> (accept alto <b><u>saxophone</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This emperor established the new 15th and 22nd legions or <em>Primigeniae</em> [[PREE-mee-GEN-ee-\"eye\"]] and ordered the construction of a new lighthouse at Boulougne [[boo-LOAN]] as part of a campaign he designed after receiving the fugitive Adminius. This emperor ordered the collection of <em>musculi</em> [[MOO-skoo-lee]], which may have been components of siege-engines but are often translated as \"seashells,\" in a story about his failed campaign. For the point, name this Roman emperor whose thwarted 40 AD invasion of Britain inspired a successful conquest by his successor, Claudius.", "answer": "<b><u>Caligula</u></b> (or <b><u>Gaius Caesar Augustus Germanicus</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on anything but the complete name if the alternate answer is given)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man survived two separate plane crashes in 1954 and was not found for 24 hours until rescuers discovered him with a bottle of gin in his hand. While an ambulance driver on the Italian front, this man nearly died from an Austro-Hungarian mortar shell. This journalist, who lived in the Finca Vigia in Cuba, reported on the last stand of Republican forces at the Ebro River, inspiring his work <em>For Whom the Bell Tolls</em>. For the point, name this Nobel laureate who drew from real-life experiences to write <em>A Farewell to Arms</em> and <em>The Sun also Rises</em>.", "answer": "Ernest <b><u>Hemingway</u></b> (or Ernest Miller <b><u>Hemingway</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Amos Kendall's \"summer tour\" pre-selected the \"pet\" replacements for this institution. The de-chartering of this institution led to the Panic of 1837 after its president, Nicholas Biddle, failed to defeat the \"hard money\" movement. The constitutionality of this organization's charter was upheld as part of the <em>McCulloch v. Maryland</em> decision, which prohibited states from taxing federal organizations. For the point, name this financial institution that was targeted in a metaphorical \"war\" by Andrew Jackson.", "answer": "<b><u>Second Bank of the United States</u></b> (or <b><u>Second Bank of the U.S.</u></b>; accept <b><u>Second</u></b> <b><u>B.U.S.</u></b>; prompt on \"Bank of the United States\" or \"Bank of the U.S.\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Partially inspired by his presence at the Council of Trent, this man executed his <em>Annunciation</em> for the Church of San Salvador. This man's nephew and apprentice Marco Vecellio [[veh-cheh-LEE-oh]] painted this artist's former patron, the Habsburg Emperor Charles V, meeting with Pope Clement VII [[the seventh]]. In a <em>A Tramp Abroad</em>, Mark Twain said \"the obscenest picture the world possesses\" is this artist's <em>Venus of Urbino</em>. For the point, name this Renaissance artist of <em>Sacred and Profane Love</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Titian</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tiziano</u></b> Vecelli)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "John Carden bet this man a beaver pelt hat that his ship, the HMS <em>Macedonian</em>, would outgun this man's USS <em>United States</em>. James Barron, who commanded the namesake vessel during the Chesapeake Affair, killed this rival officer thirteen years later in a duel over this man's critical remarks. This youngest captain in U.S. Navy history burned the captured USS <em>Philadelphia</em> in a daring raid during the Barbary Wars. The toast \"Our country, right or wrong\" was given by, for the point, which American commodore of the early 19th century?", "answer": "Stephen <b><u>Decatur</u></b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The SIT absolved this politician of wrongdoing in inciting 2002 riots that led to the Gulbarg Society massacre. Following the Uri terrorist attacks, this Prime Minister called for the diplomatic isolation of Pakistan. Mass protests against this man's administration occurred after his passage of the Citizen Amendment Act, due in part to Muslims being excluded from a path to Indian citizenship. The leader of the BJP is, for the point, which Gujarati politician who has served as the Prime Minister of India since 2014?", "answer": "Narendra <b><u>Modi</u></b> (or Narendra Damodardas <b><u>Modi</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In this nation, cameraman Alexander Lashkarava died from wounds received from an anti-LGBTQ mob in July 2021. Women soldiers in this country known as the \"Black Pantyhose Battalion\" took up arms to support Zviad Gamsakhurdia [[svee-AHD gam-SAH-kerr-DEE-ah]], who was overthrown in a 1992 coup and replaced with a military council supported by Moscow. The Medvedev regime invaded this nation in the late 2000s to prop up the republics of Abkhazia and South Ossetia. For the point, name this Caucasus nation which saw a regime change following the Rose Revolution in Tbilisi.", "answer": "<b><u>Georgia</u></b> (accept <b><u>Sakartvelo</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This is the central action performed during an annual tradition co-created by Travis Garone that began in South Australia. Every March, members of the United States Air Force engage in this action to honor triple-ace Robin Olds. A man named Emmet Pearson vowed to never stop doing this until the Vikings won a Super Bowl. A tradition that involves doing this to raise awareness for prostate cancer is called Movember. For the point, name this practice in which one goes for a period of time without performing a certain act of personal grooming.", "answer": "<b><u>Grow</u></b>ing <b><u>facial hair</u></b> (accept specific types of <b><u>facial hair</u></b> like \"beards\" or \"mustaches\"; accept <b><u>face</u></b> for \"facial\"; accept descriptive answers)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In 1935, a commission chartered by the Roosevelt administration found that one of this soldier's notable achievements took place at Sunflower Landing. During Pizarro's conquest of Peru, this man taught chess to the captive Atahualpa [[ah-tah-WAL-pah]]. This man fought a battle with Chief Tuskaloosa in what is now Alabama the year after his landing in Tampa Bay. For the point, name this Spanish explorer whose 1539 expedition across the present-day southeastern U.S. made him the first European to reach the Mississippi River.", "answer": "Hernando <b><u>de Soto</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An agreement named for this city attempted to pull the neutral Italy to the Allies by offering them the Slovenian portion of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. Jay's Treaty, which aimed to end the practice of impressment and facilitate peaceful trade, is sometimes named for this city. Following the battle of Poitiers [[pwah-tee-AY]], Edward the Black Prince acquired much of Western France through a treaty with this name. A follow-up to the Washington Naval Conference was, for the point, which agreement named for the capital city of the UK?", "answer": "<b><u>London</u></b> (accept Treaty of <b><u>London</u></b>; or <b><u>Pact</u></b> of <b><u>London</u></b>; accept <b><u>London</u></b> Naval Conference)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This practice is the only known way to get the prion disease Kuru, which is sometimes seen in the Fore people in New Guinea. The names of the Carib and Mohawk people are derived from neighboring groups' belief that those tribes engaged in this practice. Dictators Jean-Bedel Bokassa and Idi Amin were both accused of subjecting political enemies to this practice, which the Donner Party resorted to while trapped in the Sierra Nevadas. Ritually practiced by the Aztecs, for the point, what practice denotes the eating of human flesh?", "answer": "Human <b><u>Cannibalism</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The U.S. Seventh Army made use of this series of defenses during Operation Northwind, a counteroffensive which began following an advance by Johannes Blaskowitz into the Vosges [[VOHZH]] Mountains. In <em>Toward a Professional Army</em>, Charles de Gaulle advocated abandoning spending on this project in favor of mobile warfare research. The Nazi government built the Siegfried Line opposite this series of fortifications. For the point, name this \"Line\" of French fortifications in Alsace-Lorraine bypassed by a <em>blitzkrieg</em> invasion of Belgium.", "answer": "<b><u>Maginot</u></b> [[mah-jeh-NOH]] Line (or Ligne <b><u>Maginot</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A popular inspirational tale arising from this war follows Andrew Rowan's attempt to deliver a message to a pro-U.S. general. Carter Johnson led buffalo soldiers at this war's Battle of Tayacoba. U.S. foreign policy towards a country that became independent as a result of this war was governed by the Teller and Platt Amendments and included a perpetual lease on Guantanamo Bay. For the point, name this war in which the U.S. gained control of Puerto Rico and the Philippines, as well as securing Cuban independence.", "answer": "<b><u>Spanish-American</u></b> War (accept Guerra <b><u>hispano-estadounidense</u></b>; or <b><u>Guerra</u></b> <b><u>[a]hispano-americana</u></b>; accept Digmaang <b><u>Espanyol-Amerikano</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man defeated Licinius at the Battle of Chrysopolis [[kry-SAH-poh-lis]], and his eldest son, Crispus, won the Battle of the Hellespont. According to Eusebius of Caesarea, this man had a vision of the sign of the Chi-Rho [[KY-ROH]] before a battle in which he defeated Maxentius. That battle marked this man\u2019s possible conversion to Christianity and was fought on the Milvian Bridge. For the point, identify this Roman emperor who established a namesake capital at the site of Byzantium.", "answer": "<b><u>Constantine</u></b> I (or <b><u>Constantine</u></b> the Great)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Prior to the U.S. Civil War, this project's most prominent advocate was Theodore Judah, who privately lobbied James Buchanan and surveyed a future route with miner Daniel Strong. After this project's completion, its most popular line was dubbed the \"Overland Route.\" This infrastructure project was completed at Promontory Point with the tapping of the \"golden spike.\" The Union Pacific and Central Pacific were combined to complete, for the point, which railway project?", "answer": "<b><u>Transcontinental Railroad</u></b> (accept answers indicating a railroad that crosses the United States; prompt on railroad)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Confucius outlined the beneficial type of this artform as <em>yayue</em>, labelling it essential for self-cultivation in the <em>Analects</em>. Art found in Mohenjo-Daro depicts a bronze statue of a girl performing this activity, seen with her hand on her hip. Plantation slaves developed one of these artistic performances known as the \"cakewalk\" in a subtle mockery of their slaveholding owners. The Cha-Cha and Waltz are types of, for the point, what kind of rhythmic movement often done with a partner?", "answer": "<b><u>Dance</u></b> (accept <b><u>Dancing</u></b>; accept <b><u>Dancing</u></b> Girl; prompt on \"Music\")", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "This woman lost her sibling Jimmie at the Tewksbury Almshouse after their father Thomas abandoned them to move west. One woman detailed her early childhood spent with her parent and this figure in the autobiography <em>Story of My Life</em>, which was dedicated to Alexander Graham Bell. This woman adapted a system of spelling words on the palm of a hand in an effort to teach the concept of language to one student. For the point, name this teacher and lifelong companion of Helen Keller.", "answer": "Anne <b><u>Sullivan</u></b> Macy", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This building was renovated in the 19th century under the supervision of Eug\u00e8ne Viollet-le-Duc, and the <em>Magnificat</em> was sung in this location to celebrate a 1944 liberation of its surrounding city. King Louis VII [[the Seventh]] and Pope Alexander III oversaw the laying of this building's cornerstone in 1163. The wood roof known as this building's \"forest\" was completely destroyed in an April 2019 fire that started a five-year rebuilding project. For the point, name this Gothic cathedral that has stood since the 12th century in Paris.", "answer": "Cathedral of <b><u>Notre-Dame</u></b> de Paris (or <b><u>Notre Dame</u></b> Cathedral)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The U.S. made a deal with this leader to buy up the entirety of his nation's tungsten output to deprive Nazi Germany of the mineral. This leader permitted the volunteer brigade known as the \"Blue Division\" to fight for the German military during on the Eastern Front of World War Two. At the Hendaye Meeting, this leader agreed to join the Axis on the ground that he receive the entirety of French Morocco and the British possession of Gibraltar. Spain was neutral during the Second World War due to, for the point, which leader of the Falange?", "answer": "Francisco <b><u>Franco</u></b> (or Francisco <b><u>Franco</u></b> Bahamonde)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}